Sodachi Lost
End Story
忍野扇の話題に それでは改めて戻ろう
Let's return once more to the question of Oshino Ougi.
However, in the meantime, the fact remains that Oshino Ougi is just Oshino Ougi.
と言ってもやはり彼女は彼女であり 彼女は彼女でしかないのは
始めたところで改めたところで戻ったところで 根本的な話題は それでおしまいである
Oshino Ougi
Oshino
Ougi
Oshino Ougi
Oshino Ougi was just Oshino Ougi.
If she was described in the form of a novel, it would completed in a single sentence.
もしも忍野扇という存在を小説として描くのならば
たった一行で完結してしまうというわけだ
Oshino Ougi was just Oshino Ougi.
忍野扇は忍野扇だった
"Oshino Ougi was just Oshino Ougi."
Praise to the author.
めでたしめでたし
一行だ
A single sentence.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
というわけで 数学のお勉強が続いたけれど
We've primarily learned about mathematics up to this point.
最後は国語の授業と行こう
But in the last section, let us study Japanese.
国語の問題だ
This will be a Japanese question.
何々について 何字以内で答えよ
Answer the following question within the character limit.
忍野扇については既に語った通り
We have already discussed Oshino Ougi.
彼女を問題の主軸に据えるのならば
If she were the subject of a Japanese question,
[Q]
and you were tasked with describing her in four characters or less,
問題文は"忍野扇について四字以内で答えよ"で
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
[Q]
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
[Q]
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
[A]
[Q]
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
[A]
[Q]
Describe
Oshino Ougi
with four
characters
or less.
[A]
答は"忍野扇"だ
then the answer would simply be "Oshino Ougi."
Oshino Ougi
だから僕が提出する最後の問題はこうだ
Therefore, this last question I give to you is rather:
Oshino Ougi
[A]
[Q]
Oshino Ougi
[A]
[Q]
Just how big a fool is
Araragi Koyomi?
Answer in twenty
characters or less.
Your answer must
contain the name
"Oshino Ougi" once.
"阿良々木暦はどれほどに愚かなのか?"
Just how big of a fool is Araragi Koyomi?
二十字以内で答えよ
Answer in twenty characters or less.
ただし文中に必ず一度 "忍野扇"を使うこと
Your answer must contain the name "Oshino Ougi" once.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Red
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
End Story
Sodachi Lost
Part One
結局 わかったの? 阿良々木くん
Did you remember, Araragi?
老倉さんが 阿良々木くんのご両親の職業を知っていた理由は
Why Oikura knew about your parents' occupation?
ん... ああ わかったよ
Yeah, I did.
千石にも確認したから間違いない
I asked Sengoku to make sure.
いや 別にこうべを垂れつつ肯定するようなことじゃないと思うけれど
I doubt it's something so bad that you have to hang your head in shame.
こうべを垂れたくもなるさ
It makes me want to hang it in shame.
僕はどんなに頑張っても思い出せなかったのに
I couldn't remember anything, no matter how hard I tried,
羽川の言った通りにしたら すぐにわかっちゃったんだから
but when I did what you recommended, it came to be in a blink.
Honestly, you know everything, don't you, Hanekawa?
まったく羽川 お前は何でも知ってるな
何でもは知らないわよ
I don't know everything.
知ってることだけ
I just know what I know.
扇ちゃんが何を知っているのかは
だから知らないんだよね
That's why I don't know the things Ougi knows.
大丈夫だよね?
We're fine, right? She's not tailing us, right?
尾行してきてないよね? あの子
尾行って
Tailing us?
いやいや 殺し屋かなんかじゃないんだから
No, don't worry. She's not an assassin or something.
殺し屋?
An assassin?
Tailing the suspect is a detective's job, Araragi.
尾行は探偵の仕業じゃない? 阿良々木くん
ついて来てくれてたほうがありがたかったかな この場合
I think I would've liked for her to tail us, actually.
We could have shaken her off if she'd tried.
尾行してきてくれてたら 撒(ま)けたのに
神経質になり過ぎじゃないのか?
Don't you think you're being too nervous?
いや でも阿良々木くん
Well, Araragi.
尾行はされてなくとも 先回りはされてるかもしれないよ
If she's not tailing us, she might have gone on ahead.
目的地ははっきりしているんだから
She knows where we're going.
調べるならそっちのほうがリスクが低いしね
That's a safe bet if she wants to know what we're doing.
神経質になり過ぎってことはないよ
I'm not being too nervous.
If that's not it, then you're just overestimating Oshino Ougi.
神経質になり過ぎてないんだったら 羽川
お前扇ちゃんを高く評価し過ぎだって
確かにあの子は忍野の姪で
そこそこ頭がいいところはあるみたいだけれど
I mean, she's Oshino Meme's niece and seems to be pretty smart,
けどやっぱ子供って言うか
but don't you think she's still kind of a child,
一年生って言うか
kind of immature,
可愛げのある感じじゃないか
kind of cute?
ああいう子が忍野みたいにならないよう教導するのが
先輩としての僕達の役目であり
It's our job as her elders to make sure she doesn't end up like Oshino.
それが忍野への恩返しにもなるだろう
That way, we can pay back some of our debt to him, too.
忍野さんへの恩返し ね
Pay back our debt to Oshino, huh?
うん それは立派な心がけだ
Yes, that's very admirable.
感心感心
I'm moved.
てっきり阿良々木くんは またも登場した可愛い後輩に
夢中になっているのかと思っちゃってた
And there I was, fearing you were yet again
head over heels for some cute girl you just met.
"Yet again?"
またもって
神原さんのときにも阿良々木くんって
似たようなことになってなかった?
Didn't something similar happen when you met Kanbaru?
その心がけが本心なのであれば
If you're serious about what you just said,
やめてよね クラスが大変なことになっているときに
then just refrain from fussing over younger girls in a way people could misconstrue.
後輩にかまけるような、誤解される振る舞いは
I need you to help me put the class back in order right now.
I will keep it in mind.
肝に銘じるよ
よろしい
That will suffice.
Let me ask this to make sure.
確認するけれど
阿良々木くんは扇ちゃんのフィールドワークに同行するまで
Until you tagged along on Ougi's investigation,
老倉さんとの中学時代の思い出を忘れていたんだよね?
you didn't remember anything about yourself and Oikura in middle school?
ん... いや 違う違う 逆逆
Uh... No, no. It's the other way around.
僕のフィールドワークに扇ちゃんが同行してくれたんだ
Ougi tagged along on my investigation.
扇ちゃんは基本的に僕についてきてくれただけだ
Ougi just went with me.
僕が老倉を思い出す 手伝いをしてくれただけなんだ
She just helped me remember Oikura.
なんだかうまく伝わらないなー
You're misunderstanding what I mean.
私がちゃんと表現できてないのかな
Maybe I'm not finding the right words.
私から見たら あんなに危険な子はいないんだけど
The way I see it, no other girl is that dangerous.
危険?
Dangerous? You mean Oikura?
老倉の話か?
ほら 噛み合わない
See? We're just not on the same wavelength.
It's like you're dodging the topic on purpose.
まるで阿良々木くんがわざと論点をズラしているみたい
まあいいでしょう
Well, whatever.
きっと今はそういう話ができないってことなんでしょうよ
I suppose you're not able to talk about it right now.
羽川 もしも扇ちゃんが老倉に
悪意をもっているらしいと考えているなら
Hanekawa. Are you thinking Ougi might bear Oikura some kind of ill will?
それは違うぞ
I'm pretty sure that's not the case.
そもそも扇ちゃんは老倉と会ったこともないんだから
They've never even met.
そんな心配はしていないよ 阿良々木くん
That isn't what I'm worried about.
扇ちゃんが老倉さんに目をつけただなんて
そんなこと つゆほども心配していない
I'm not worried in the slightest
that Ougi has her eyes on Oikura.
私が心配しているのは
The one I'm worried about is—
のは?
Is?
だから 阿良々木くんだよ
—is you, Araragi.
あなたはよくわからないものに目をつけられたのかもしれない
Something we understand poorly might have its eyes set on you.
よくわからないもの?
Something we understand poorly?
よくないもの かもしれないけど
Or something that's just bad.
正直 守りきれるかどうか自信がないな
Frankly, I'm not sure if I can protect you.
守り...
Protect—
You told me that what happened
during summer break was hell itself.
阿良々木くんは春休みのことを地獄って呼んでいたけれど
阿良々木くんの本当の受難(じゅなん)はこれからなのかもね
But this might only be the beginning of your Passion.
僕達は 羽川翼委員長と阿良々木暦副委員長は 目的地
And so, class rep Hanekawa Tsubasa and vice rep Araragi Koyomi arrived at their destination.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
White
Black
老倉育の現住所に到着した
Oikura Sodachi's present abode.
Sodachi Lost
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
The former class rep Oikura Sodachi did not come to school again the next day.
老倉育 元学級委員長は ある翌日から
再び学校に来なくなった
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
そして その辺の不穏な空気を敏感に察してだろう
Most likely sensing the ominous atmosphere in class,
彼女もまたあの日以来学校に来ていない
Senjougahara remained absent as well.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
というわけで 阿良々木くん
Okay, Araragi.
今日の放課後 お見舞いに行こうと思うんだけど
Basically, I want to check up on those two after school.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
戦場ヶ原さんと老倉さんの
Senjougahara and Oikura.
とにかく時間がないから 手分けしてかかろうと思うんだ
We don't have that much time, so we should split up.
Which one do you want to visit?
戦場ヶ原さんと老倉さん
阿良々木くんは どっちのお見舞いに行きたい?
Senjougahara or Oikura?
阿良々木くんが決めていいよ
You can decide freely.
Sodachi Lost
恋人を見舞うか
Should I visit my girlfriend?
仇敵(きゅうてき)を見舞うか
Should I visit my mortal enemy?
なかなかの究極の選択ではあったが
僕は後者を選ぶことにした
After some deliberation over this
extraordinary decision, I chose the latter.
手分けして行動することにしたはずなのに
のちに羽川と合流している理由?
Then perhaps you're wondering why, after having decided to split up, I went there together with Hanekawa?
Her Passion
それはこういう経緯だ
Here are the particulars.
Hey. If it isn't Araragi.
あっれー? 阿良々木先輩じゃないですかあ
扇ちゃん...
Ougi...
扇ちゃん... 今帰り?
On your way home, Ougi?
帰り?
Home?
えーっと... いや
Uh, no.
何を言っているんですか 阿良々木先輩
What are you talking about, Araragi?
私達はここで待ち合わせをしていたんじゃないですか
We promised to meet here, didn't we?
校門のところで三時四十二分に待ち合わせって
約束したじゃないですか
Didn't we promise we'd meet here, in front of the school, at 3:42 PM?
さすが阿良々木先輩
How commendable.
時間ぴったり
You're right on time.
正確だなあ
そういうところ真面目なんだものなあ
Sometimes you can be reliable and punctual—
この愚か者は
even as a fool.
Naoetsu Private High School Entrance
Gosh, I sure am happy.
わーい 嬉しいなあ
Naoetsu Private High Scho
阿良々木先輩がこれから
回転しないお寿司屋さんに連れて行ってくれるだなんて
Never would I have thought that Araragi would treat me to really nice sushi.
I promised you that?!
そんな約束をしたのか!? 僕は!?
Of course you did.
Naoetsu Private High School Entrance
したじゃないですか
私の転校祝いだって
You said it would be my welcoming party.
転校祝いに回転しない寿司って...
Expensive sushi as a welcoming party?
Just what is being welcomed here at my school?
いったい何が転校してきたんだよ 僕の学校に
ごめんな 扇ちゃん
I'm sorry, Ougi.
残念ながらきみとの約束は守れそうにない
I regret to say that I don't believe I can keep our promise.
おや
Oh, my.
なんですかその格好いい台詞は
What makes you say something so dashing?
約束を破りながらも格好いい台詞は
Even as you break our promise, you show off.
さてはお金を持ってませんね
Are you broke or something?
ちょっとこれから僕は
老倉の家に行かなくちゃいけないんだよ 扇ちゃん
I have to go to Oikura's house now, Ougi.
To that decrepit ruin?
ほほう? またあの廃屋に行くのですか?
んにゃ 廃屋じゃなくて 現住所のほう
No, where she actually lives now.
Huh.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
I've become
way too talkative
in front of Ougi.
何すんだ!?
What are you doing?!
いえ お口のチャックを開けてみました
I opened the zipper on your mouth.
チャックというか マジックテープみたいでしたけれどね
It was more like adhesive tape, actually.
もう少し聞かせてくださいよ お願いですから
Please, tell me more.
What happened?
何があったんです?
すさまじいスピードで老倉先輩を攻略しているじゃないですか
You seem to be well on your way down Sodachi's route.
日進月歩ですねえ
Slow and steady wins the race.
いったいどういう経過を辿ったのか報告しなさい
Tell me what happened since we last met,
愚か者
fool.
いや 攻略とか そんなんじゃないよ
I'm not trying to woo her or anything.
訪ね合うんじゃなくて
一方的に押しかけるみたいなもんだし
She didn't really consent to this visit, you see?
昨日からあいつ また学校に来なくなって
She stopped coming to school again yesterday.
一昨日だって来てないようなものなんだけれども
Even the day before yesterday she might as well not have been there.
Huh.
I was forced to explain.
Naoetsu Private High School
So it went.
ってわけなんだよ
So it went, huh?
ってわけなんですか
僕もまだ詳しく聞いたわけじゃないけれど
I don't really know what's going on exactly,
今のあいつは 親元を離れて生活しているみたいで
but it looks like she's not living with her parents anymore.
親元を離れて? ほほう
Without her parents?
では 親戚に保護されてということになるのでしょうか
Then I assume some other relative is her guardian?
いや 一人暮らしみたい
No, she's living alone.
へえ そりゃあまた 面白いなあ
Well, isn't that fascinating?
だから扇ちゃんの言ってた通り
I think you were right about what happened
five years ago. Her parents probably divorced.
五年前に 両親の離婚だかなんだかがあったんだろうな
Her family imploded.
家庭崩壊と言うか
Then she came back here two years ago.
それで二年前 この土地に帰ってきた
なるほどねえ
I see.
出任せの推理が当たりましたか
So my wild theory turned out to be spot on.
しかしそ 阿良々木先輩 愚かなる阿良々木先輩
But, Araragi, my wonderful fool.
つまり阿良々木先輩はこれから
事実上一人暮らしの女の子を訪ねようとしているわけじゃあないですか
Am I to presume that you're now going
to visit Oikura, a girl that lives all alone?
これはよくありません
This will not do.
It won't?
よくないかな
よくないです よくないです
Not at all.
紳士にあるまじき行為ですよ
It is unbecoming of a gentleman.
一人暮らしの女子を
男子が単身で訪ねていくなど その仲を疑われても仕方がありませんよ
Many will craft theories about your relationship if you visit her alone.
It's really not something you should do when you have a girlfriend.
パートナー持ちの身でなさるような行為ではありませんねえ
決意はお堅いようですねえ
You seem quite determined.
回転しないお寿司 楽しみだったんですけれどね
I was really looking forward to
that expensive sushi restaurant.
じゃ 扇ちゃん
So long, Ougi.
ああそうだ!
Oh, I know.
I just had a very good idea, Araragi.
いいことを思いつきましたよ 阿良々木先輩
不肖この私が その家庭訪問に同行しましょう!
I will accompany you on your visitation.
え 扇ちゃんが?
You would?
それはありがたいけど...
That's good, but...
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
Huh? Is it good?
つまり単身でなければいいんですよ
Visiting her alone is the crux.
特にほら 私は女子ですからね
Considering that I, too, am a girl,
一緒にいれば老倉先輩の心も
いくらか和(なご)むんじゃあないでしょうか
I believe I can console her to some degree.
She's not the sort to be consoled by just any girl.
女子が相手だからといって
和むような奴じゃないんだが
Would a younger girl console her a little?
ご存知の通り 私は聞き上手ですからね
You do know that I'm a great listener.
ひょっとすると老倉先輩から
いろいろと聞き出せるかもしれませんよ
We might be able to extract all sorts of stories from Oikura.
Extract?
聞き出せる
阿良々木先輩はこれまで
学級会のときのことや中学一年生の夏休みのことを想起して
You recalled the class meeting and what happened in middle school.
過去の彼女を思い出しはしましたけれど
You remember what she was like back then,
but you still can't talk to her normally.
どっこい今の彼女と
全然ちゃんと話せていないじゃないですか
言い合いにならないよう
私が間に入って差し上げますよ
I can be the relay between you so it doesn't get out of hand.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
なあに ここまでくれば乗りかかった船です
You might as well be hanged for a sheep as a lamb.
私に骨を折らせてくださいよ
Let me do some work.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
んじゃ 扇ちゃん お願いするよ
All right, Ougi. Please help me.
はい
All right.
お願いされました
I've been asked to help.
Don't ask her!
Naoetsu Private High School
お願いしちゃ駄目!
Sodachi Lost
Don't ask her to help, Araragi.
お願いしちゃ駄目だよ 阿良々木くん
羽川...
Hanekawa?
駄目だって ほら
クラスの内輪揉めに 後輩を巻き込んじゃ
Do you really want to bother an underclassman with our private affairs?
Oh. So that's what you mean? That's the reason?
Indeed, it's not a good thing to rope outsiders into a private affair.
扇ちゃ―
Ougi—
Hold on, hold on.
変な遠慮をしないでくださいよ 阿良々木先輩
There is no need to be shy.
That would hurt my feelings.
そっちのほうが傷つきますって
Please, don't worry about me.
私のことなら気にしないでくださいよ
まったく構いませんから
I don't mind at all.
お構いなくですから
Don't hold back.
I'm shocked you would be so cold to me.
むしろここに来て
そんなよそよそしいことを言われるほうがショックですよ
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
ガーンです
Gasp!
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
Don't ruin our relationship, Araragi.
私と阿良々木先輩の仲じゃないですか
And what kind of relationship would that be?
きみと阿良々木くんが どんな仲なのかな?
きみと阿良々木くんは
ほんの一昨々日(さきおととい) 知り合ったばかりなんでしょ?
Didn't you only meet three days ago?
ええ そうですね
Yes, we did.
でもまあ 人付き合いというのは
必ずしも時間ではありませんからねえ
But the depth of one's relationship is not a function of time.
Why, I feel like we really hit it off in no time at all.
私としては阿良々木先輩とは
短時間ですっかり意気投合してしまったつもりでいたんですが
謎の教室に閉じこめられたり
We were locked in a classroom together.
We explored a ruin.
廃屋に冒険に行ったり
We have so many unusual memories together.
普通ではありえないような体験を共にしましたからねえ
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
ねえ阿良々木先輩?
Right, Araragi?
Yeah...
ん? ああ そりゃあ...
ああ うん その件については聞いているわ
Yes, I've been informed.
阿良々木くんが 私の大切な友人がとても世話になったみたいで
It looks like my dear friend Araragi is in your debt.
お礼を言わなきゃいけないと思っていたの
Let me thank you.
But if I had been with him, I'd have done a better job.
だけどまあ 私ならもっとうまくやったけど
へえ そうですか
Is that so?
ええ そうでしょうね
I suppose it must be.
きっと羽川先輩のほうがうまくやったに違いありませんね
I'm sure you would have done better.
なにせあなたは天才でいらっしゃる
You are a genius, after all.
ええ そりゃあもう 叔父さんから聞いていますよ
Yes, my uncle has told me.
叔父さん それは忍野さんのことを言っているのかしら
Your uncle... Oshino, you mean?
Yes. I am his niece.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Red
ええ 姪ですから
ただしまあ その天才性も
発揮されなければ無意味ですねえ
But what is the benefit of genius unused?
実際 そのとき
阿良々木先輩のそばにいたのは私なわけですし
The one who was actually there to help him was I.
叔父さんも怖がったというあなたの天才性
I hear even my uncle was afraid of your genius.
ええ だけれど そういう視点から見れば
聞いていたほどでもありませんね
The way I see it, it isn't as remarkable as I was told.
You see, from the stories I would have assumed you would come to his aid in peril.
私が聞いていた羽川翼ならば 阿良々木先輩の危機に際して
そこにいないなんてことはなかったでしょうから
I can only conclude that your genius has declined since its heyday.
もっとうまくやったというのは
全盛期ならばという意味ではないんですかねえ
おいおい 扇ちゃん
Hey, Ougi.
Is this really warranted?
そういう言いかたはないんじゃないか
言っていいことと悪いことがあるぞ
You're clearly going too far.
きみが羽川の何を知っていると言うんだい
What do you even know about her?
私は何も知りませんよ
I don't know anything.
あなたが知っているんです 阿良々木先輩
You know everything, Araragi.
羽川先輩の 過去と現在
そして 未来についてはね
You know her past, her present, and her future, too.
そう 確かに本来 私が口を出すようなことではありません
そこについては
You are correct. I have no right to interrupt your narration.
まあ 羽川先輩
Anyway, Hanekawa.
あなたと張り合うほど馬鹿じゃありませんよ 私は
I'm not stupid enough to try competing with you.
あなたに失礼を働いて
大好きな阿良々木先輩に嫌われたくもありませんしね
I also have no wish to belittle you
and be hated by Araragi in return.
どうぞ 棲(す)み分けて行きましょうよ
Let us go our separate ways again.
ごめんください
Please.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
どうぞどうぞ あなたはこれから戦場ヶ原先輩の家に
お見舞いに行くのでしょう?
Were you not on your way to Senjougahara?
そちらの家のほうが遠そうですし
早く行かれたほうがいいんじゃないですか?
Her house is farther away,
so I recommend you be on your way.
遠そう...?
Farther?
Rest easy.
ご安心ください
If you don't wish to see your beloved friend Araragi asking a younger girl for help, we can change the rules.
あなたの大切な友人である阿良々木先輩が 後輩に"お願い"するなんて
姿を見たくないと言うのであれば そういう形は取りませんよ
だって元々 私が言い出したことですしね
I mean, I suggested it to begin with.
私が勝手に 阿良々木先輩の動きに
同道するという形を取りましょう
I will simply accompany him of my own accord.
背後霊(はいごれい)のように
Like a spirit guide.
それなら構わないわけですよね?
Does that sound acceptable?
ほら 推理小説ではよく見かける
押し掛け助手みたいな感じですよ
You know, I'll be like those uninvited sidekicks you see so often in mystery novels.
押し掛け助手...
Uninvited sidekicks?
なにやら困っている阿良々木先輩を
放ってはおけませんからね
How could I abandon Araragi to his tribulations?
私は阿良々木先輩をお助け申し上げたいのですよ
I want to save Araragi.
人は一人で勝手に助かるだけ
People can only save themselves,
じゃないのかしら?
right?
それは叔父さんのスタンスです
That's my uncle's stance.
私のスタンスはどちらかというと鶴(つる)の恩返しでして
My own stance would be the like The Grateful Crane.
鶴の恩返し?
The Grateful Crane?
まあ 笠地蔵(かさじぞう)でもいいんですがね
Or perhaps Six Little Statues.
要は過剰な恩返しというのが主義なんですよ
Essentially, I hold that debts must be repaid many times over.
恩 返し過ぎだろ!
A lot of interest!
って言う
You see?
阿良々木先輩は 転校したてのこんな私に
とても親切にしてくださいましたし
Araragi was very kind to me after I transferred here.
その恩は身体を張ってでも
お返ししたく思うところでして
I would like to repay that debt even at risk to myself.
阿良々木くん
Araragi.
予定変更
The plan has changed.
私も老倉さんの家に行くわ
I'm going to see Oikura.
阿良々木くんと一緒に
Together with you, Araragi.
それで文句はないわけだよね? 扇ちゃんは
Ougi, that would be enough, right?
阿良々木くんが一人で 男子一人で
老倉さんの家に行くことが問題だったんだから
You didn't like that Araragi, a man, was going to a girl's house alone.
私が同行すれば その点何の問題もない
If I accompany him, we have no problem.
No excuse for you.
何の口実もない
Isn't that right?
そうだよね?
問題のあるなしはともかくとして あなたは戦場ヶ原先輩の家を
訪ねなきゃいけないんじゃありませんでしたっけ? 羽川先輩
Problem or not, shouldn't you be going to see Senjougahara, Hanekawa?
感心しませんねえ 親友のほうを後回しにするなんて
It isn't very nice
to leave your dear friend for later.
元々 戦場ヶ原さんとは長い話になりそうだったからね
I always expected it would take a little longer.
今晩は泊めてもらうことにする
I'll just sleep at her place later.
久し振りに戦場ヶ原さんの家で
パジャマパーティでも開くわ
It's been a while since the last pajama party.
Pajama
party?
それでいいでしょう?
You should be fine with that.
だって 私のほうがあなたより
うまくやれるんだから
I am, after all, more capable than you.
うまくやればいいってものでもないんですよ
この世の中は
Merely being capable isn't enough to solve everything in this world.
うまくやり過ぎるのも
それはそれでバランスを欠くものです
You can also be too capable and damage the balance.
中庸(ちゅうよう)には収まりませんからねえ
The middle ground is important.
あなたはそれをよくご存知かと思いますが
I believe you know that very well.
Well, for better or worse, Araragi is the one who decides this, not me.
まあ いいか悪いかはともかく
それを決めるのは私ではなく阿良々木先輩ですねえ
私と行くのか
Will you go with me?
羽川先輩と行くのか
Will you go with Hanekawa?
阿良々木先輩 あなたが決めてくださいな
Please decide, Araragi.
決定権を委(ゆだ)ねます
You have full authority.
私も羽川先輩も
あなたの決断に全面的に従いますよ
Both Hanekawa and I will obey your decision without fail.
ねえ?
Right?
そうだね
Yes.
阿良々木くんが決めて
Decide, Araragi.
これは強要できることじゃあないもの
We can't force ourselves on you.
You know, Araragi.
ねえ 阿良々木先輩
いけませんよねえ
You owe so much to Hanekawa.
大切な恩人である羽川先輩に
個人的な事情で迷惑をかけるようなことがあっては
How could you burden her with even more of your petty problems?
内輪というなら
羽川先輩だってその輪の外にいますよ
Come to think of it, she has nothing to do with this private affair either.
羽川先輩を困らせるようなことを
阿良々木先輩が望むわけがありませんよねえ
Surely, Araragi, you don't wish to make life harder for Hanekawa.
Yes, that is very true.
What she says rings so true.
I promise you, Araragi.
約束しましょう 阿良々木先輩
私と一緒に行ってくれれば そこにどんな謎があれ
またもひとつの 解決を提示してさしあげると
If you go with me, then I promise I will solve
whatever mysteries may lie in wait there for us.
If you promise so much...
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
約束するわ 阿良々木くん
I promise you, Araragi,
私と一緒に行ってくれれば
that if you go with me
おっぱいを触らせてあげる
you can touch my boobs.
Sodachi Lost
Oikura
ここの４４４号室か
Number 444 here, huh?
どうやらあまり信心深くない管理会社のご様子だな
The property management firm doesn't seem very dutiful.
マンションって言うより これは団地かな
It's just a cheap apartment block.
She probably receives some kind of subsidy.
たぶん 何らかの補助を受けているんだろうね 老倉さん
補助?
Subsidy?
うん 公的な
Yeah, welfare.
それで住居を紹介してもらったって感じかな
And they put her into this apartment building.
僕が新たに知った 老倉と僕との
小学生時代の馴(な)れ初(そ)め
I now recall the budding relationship Oikura and I had in grade school.
しかし千石でも覚えていたようなことを
どうして僕は忘れていたのだろう?
But why did I forget something even Sengoku remembered?
いや 決して忘れていたわけではなく
No, I didn't forget it.
思えば僕は冷たい奴なのかもしれないな
The more I think about it,
I might just be a really cold person.
そういや 千石のことだって忘れていたんだし
I had forgotten about Sengoku too.
会っても最初はわからなかったし
I didn't even recognize her at first.
それはでも 仕方ないとは思うけれどね
I think that's fairly normal.
Neither Sengoku nor Oikura left a
lasting impression on you at the time.
千石ちゃんとも老倉さんとも 当時
印象に残るような関わりはなかったんでしょう?
じゃ 阿良々木くん ちょっと待ってて
All right, Araragi. Wait here.
ん? この階段でか?
On the stairs?
どうして?
Why?
だって老倉さん 一人暮らしじゃない
Because Oikura is living alone.
インターホンを押して
パジャマ姿や部屋着のままで出てきて
What if she answered the door in her pajamas or a t-shirt?
それを阿良々木くんに見られたりしたら
恥ずかしがるかもしれないから
She might not want to be seen by you looking like that.
End Story 1       Sodachi Lost Part One
Black
誰よ
Who's there?
なんだったんだろう
しかし改めて あの鬼気迫る対決構造は
Honestly, what was going on there during that terrifying showdown?
多くの人はひょっとすると誤解しているかもしれないが 別に僕は彼女の胸部に惹かれて
扇ちゃんではなく羽川をパートナーに選んだわけではない
I'm sure many have misunderstood, but I did not pick Hanekawa entranced by her bosom.
あの羽川をしてそこまで言わせる現状に ただならぬものを感じたからこそ
あの二者択一で 彼女をパートナーに指名したのである
I chose her because only something extraordinary would have driven her to offer that.
扇ちゃんには悪かったけどな...
I feel sorry for Ougi.
ちゃんとフォローを入れよう
I have to be nice to her later.
そういうこともできる奴になろう これからは
Yes, I'll help her. I can do it.
そうだな 回転しない寿司はともかく
回転する寿司にでも連れていってあげて
Maybe a high-class sushi is too much for now, but a budget sushi place sounds good.
阿良々木くん
Araragi...
いいよ 出てきて
It's fine. You go in.
出てきてって... でも
Really? But...
這入っていいってさ 中に
You can go in.
ただし 先にネタバレしておくけれど
Let me spoil the surprise right now.
あの子 パジャマ姿のままだから
She is in fact wearing her pajamas.
ん? あれ でも
お前はそういうのを回避しようとしていたんじゃないのか?
Weren't you trying to avoid that?
"阿良々木が来たことを理由に着替えるような労をとりたくない"んだって
"A visit by Araragi is not worth the trouble of changing."
頑張って説得したんだけれど
言えば言うほど意固地(いこじ)になって
I tried to convince her, but she became more stubborn by the minute.
絶対に着替えない
"I won't change."
"Pester me any more and I'll talk to him naked."
これ以上言うなら裸で出迎えると言うので
折れました
I lost.
安心しろ
Don't worry.
さすがの僕でもこの状況で
女子のパジャマにはしゃぐほどには軽薄ではない
Not even I am so superficial that I'd get excited
over a girl in her pajamas in such a grave situation.
どうだか
Really, now?
私の胸目当てな人が何を言っても
You're here for my breasts, aren't you?
She didn't understand my motivation at all.
門が開かれた以上
こちらも踏み込まないわけにはいかない
When the fortress throws open its gates,
they must be stormed.
それが宣戦布告のような開城であっても
僕は受けて立たねばならない
I must accept the challenge, even if the
open gates bespeak a declaration of war.
それが僕の
老倉育の幼なじみとしての僕の役割なのだろうから
That is my lot as Oikura's childhood friend.
I hear your laughter near me
You were supposed to be there forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter a ways away
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again